[Music]
you cannot square the circle using
classical tools but you can if you use
other techniques
if we let b be greater than zero then
the polar curve r equals b times theta
is called the archimedean spiral and it
looks like this
let's use the archimedean spiral to
square the circle
start with a radius a greater than zero
then
consider the circle of radius a centered
at the origin like this
[Music]
this circle
has an area given by pi times the radius
squared
so the area of the circle is equal to pi
times a squared
extend the radius to the other side
creating a line segment of length two a
and then draw the archimedean spiral a
times theta
this spiral intersects the y axis at the
y coordinate a pi over two
so we can draw a rectangle using these
two line segments and the rectangle has
lengths 2a and a pi over 2.
therefore we see that the area of the
rectangle
must be a pi over 2 times 2a which is pi
a squared or the area of the circle
now let's square the rectangle
to do this we can draw the circle
with radius given by xy which is the
short edge of the rectangle and we can
extend
line segment xz out to this circle to
create a point called e
now use e and z
to find the midpoint
which we'll call m
[Music]
next
draw the circle centered at m
with radius m z
like this
[Music]
then extend
the line segment y x
with a half chord down to the circle
creating an intersection point s
we can use the line segment x s
to draw a square like this
[Music]
according to the intersecting chords
theorem we see that x s multiplied by x
s
is going to be equal to xz multiplied by
xe
but because xe equals xy
that means that the area of the square
and the area of the rectangle must be
equal
putting these three facts together
we see that the area of the square is
equal to the area of the rectangle which
in turn is equal to the area of the
original circle
but this means
that we have used the archimedean spiral
to square the original circle
[Music]
you